Herbert A. Philbrick Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Herbert A. Philbrick Papers 1849-1997 1940-1993
MSS84356
Philbrick, Herbert A. (Herbert Arthur), 1915-1993
127,700 items
295 containers plus 1 oversize plus 1 top secret
117.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Anticommunist activist and counterspy. Correspondence, writings, speeches, television scripts, subject files, and other papers relating primarily to Philbrick's role as a leading anticommunist spokesman, his activities as an informant for the Federal Bureau of Investigation while he was a member of the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA), and the television program based on his autobiography, I Led 3 Lives: Citizen, “Communist,” Counterspy.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bales, James D., 1915-1995--Correspondence.; Foster, William Z., 1881-1961--Trials, litigation, etc.; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972--Correspondence.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963--Assassination.; Loeb, William, 1905-1981--Correspondence.; McDowell, Arthur G.--Correspondence.; Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1892-1971--Correspondence.; Philbrick, Herbert A. (Herbert Arthur), 1915-1993.; Philbrick, Herbert A. (Herbert Arthur), 1915-1993. I led 3 lives: citizen, "Communist," counterspy (1952); Reid, Ogden R. (Ogden Rogers), 1925-2019--Correspondence.; Roche, Anthony M.; Wallace, Henry A. (Henry Agard), 1888-1965--Correspondence.; Welch, Robert, 1899-1985--Correspondence.
Organizations
America's Future (Organization); American Youth for Democracy.; Cambridge Youth Council (Cambridge, Mass.); Christian Anti-Communism Crusade.; Communist Party of the United States of America (Mass.); Communist Party of the United States of America.; Constructive Action, Inc.; Council Against Communist Aggression (U.S.); Massachusetts Political Action Committee.; Massachusetts. Special Commission to Study and Investigate Communism and Subversive Activities and Related Matters in the Commonwealth.; Progressive Citizens of America.; U.S. Press Association.; United States Anti-Communist Congress.; United States. Congress. House--Elections, 1948.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities.; United States. Congress. Senate. Committee on the Judiciary. Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws.; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation.; Young Americans for Freedom.; Young Communist League of the U.S.
Subjects
Anti-communist movements--United States--History.; Presidents--United States--Election--1948.; Subversive activities--United States.; Undercover operations--United States.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.
Places
Massachusetts--Politics and government--1865-1950.; New England--Politics and government.
Titles
I led 3 lives (Television program); Let freedom ring (Radio program)
Occupations
Political activists.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Herbert A. Philbrick, anticommunist activist and counterspy, were given to the Library of Congress by his daughter, Dawn Philbrick Lambert, in 1998. Two additions were given by her in 2000 and 2017.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Sound and video recordings have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. Some photographs and posters have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Eight translations of I Lived 3 Lives: Citizen, "Communist," Counterspy have been transferred to the Asian Division and the African and Middle Eastern Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Herbert A. Philbrick Papers. Patrons are encouraged to contact these divisions in advance of a research visit.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Herbert A. Philbrick are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified material in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified items.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1915, May 11 Born, Boston, Mass.
1938 Graduated, Lincoln Technical Institute of Northeastern University, Boston, Mass.
1939 Married Eva Gertrude Luscombe (divorced 1967) Sales representative, Holmes Direct Mail Service, Cambridge, Mass.
1940 Organizer and chairman, Cambridge Youth Council, Cambridge, Mass. Reported suspicions of communist control of Cambridge Youth Council to Boston, Mass., office, Federal Bureau of Investigation
1941 Began reporting to Federal Bureau of Investigation on actions of Communist Party
1942 Joined Young Communist League
1942 1949 Assistant advertising director, Paramount Theaters Division of New England, M & P Theatres Co., Boston, Mass.
1944 Joined Communist Party
1949 Testified in federal court as surprise witness against eleven Communist Party leaders indicted for violation of the Smith Act
1951 Testified before hearings of the House Committee on Un-American Activities regarding Communist Party activities in the Boston, Mass., area “I Led 3 Lives” serialized in the New York Herald Tribune
1951 1957 Lectured on anticommunist topics
1952 Published I Led 3 Lives: Citizen, “Communist,” Counterspy. New York: McGraw-Hill.
1952 1958 Wrote syndicated column “Red Underground ” for the New York Herald Tribune
1953 1956 Technical advisor for television program I Led 3 Lives
1961 1962 Prepared series of five-minute television programs, The Red Report
1963 1969 Wrote newsletters, Dollar Hollar, Herb Philbrick's News Bulletin, Peoples Voice, and Schick Razor's Edge
1964 Candidate for delegate-at-large from New Hampshire to the Republican National Convention for presidential candidate Barry M. Goldwater
1967 1969 National Director, United States Anti-Communist Congress
1968 Married Shirley J. Brown
1969 1977 Editor and publisher, Washington Exclusive, U.S. Press Association
1972 Published I Led 3 Lives: Citizen, “Communist,” Counterspy, revised edition. Washington, D.C.: Capitol Hill Press
1976 1977 Writer-editor, Division of Organization and Personnel, United States Nuclear Regulatory Agency, Washington, D.C.
1977 1979 Store manager, Fletcher's Paint Works, Hampton, N.H.
1982 circa 1989 Court reporter and free-lance writer for Rockingham County, N.H., newspapers
1990 1993 President, Constructive Action
1993, Aug. 16 Died, North Hampton, N.H.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Herbert Arthur Philbrick (1915-1993) span the years 1849-1997, with the bulk of the material dating from 1940 to 1993. They relate primarily to Philbrick's interests and activities as a leading anticommunist spokesman from the 1950s through the early 1970s whose concern with the threat of communism continued until his death. Philbrick became a public figure in 1949 when he was a government witness in the trial of eleven leaders of the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA) indicted for violation of the Smith Act. During his testimony, Philbrick revealed that for the previous nine years he had functioned as an undercover agent, serving as an informant for the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) while an active member of the CPUSA. He subsequently wrote an autobiography, I Led 3 Lives: Citizen, “Communist,” Counterspy, which became the basis of a television series in the 1950s. In addition to documenting Philbrick's life and activities, his papers are a source of information on the anticommunist movement in general featuring prominent individuals and organizations and containing correspondence, newsletters, and press clippings from throughout the country. The collection is organized in ten series: General Correspondence, Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA), I Led 3 Lives, Subject File, Speeches and Writings, Miscellany, 2001 Addition, 2023 Addition, Oversize, and Top Secret.
The General Correspondence series consists primarily of letters received by Philbrick, with copies of some of his outgoing correspondence. Although correspondence relating to specific activities or individuals is filed by topic in other series, this series contains correspondence from friends, colleagues, and the general public filed by date. Frequent topics include communism, religion, reactions to Philbrick's lectures and writings, and comments on specific events and individuals.
The Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA) series focuses on Philbrick's activities in the party, particularly in the New England area. A section on the Federal Bureau of Investigation contains reports to the agency in which Philbrick, often using the pseudonym “George Lockwood,” described activities of organizations in Massachusetts that were controlled by communists and provided accounts of the events, meetings, and individuals he dealt with when he joined the Young Communist League, the Communist Party, and the Education Commission of the Massachusetts Communist Party. Organizations mentioned include the Cambridge Youth Council, American Youth for Democracy, the Massachusetts Political Action Committee, and the Progressive Citizens of America. Events described include the congressional campaign of Anthony M. Roche and the presidential campaign of Henry Agard Wallace.
A party activities section in the series contains correspondence, pamphlets, fliers, and other material collected or created by Philbrick. His assignments often involved using his advertising experience and printing skills in his work for the party, and he would collect and send the FBI copies of the materials he created and printed. A testimony section relates to remarks Philbrick made to a number of investigating bodies from 1949 to 1967 regarding communists and their activities in the United States, including testimony in United States District Court in the trial of United States v. William Z. Foster and at hearings of the House Committee on Un-American Activities, the Senate Committee on the Judiciary Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Security Laws, and the Massachusetts Special Commission to Study and Investigate Communism and Subversive Activities and Related Matters in the Commonwealth.
The series related to I Led 3 Lives features Philbrick's autobiography and the various formats in which it appeared, including a book, newspaper serialization, and a television series. The largest sections relate to the book and the television series. The book section includes outlines, summaries, and sets of drafts. Documents indicate that Philbrick worked closely with Fendall Yerxa in the preparation of his autobiography. A serialized version of the book appeared first in the New York Herald Tribune. The television section contains material relating to the syndicated television series produced from 1953 to 1956 by Ziv Television Programs, Inc. in which Richard Carlson starred as Philbrick. Philbrick served as a technical consultant to the project, and the files contain plot outlines and comments he prepared as well as scripts sent to him for approval. Other material includes correspondence relating to personal appearances Philbrick made in support of the program.
The Subject File is the largest series in the collection and contains information on people, groups, and issues of interest to Philbrick, especially communism and the Cold War. Many of the most extensive files relate to his involvement with anticommunist, conservative, and religious organizations, such as America's Future, Constructive Action, the Council Against Communist Aggression, United States Anti-Communist Congress, U.S. Press Association, and Young Americans for Freedom. A major aspect of Philbrick's work with another such group, the Christian Anti-Communism Crusade and its leader, Frederick C. Schwarz, was his participation in their anticommunism schools. Additional material related to Philbrick's work with the schools is filed in a speaking engagements section of the Speeches and Writings series. A Federal Bureau of Investigation file contains correspondence and memoranda that Philbrick continued to send to the FBI in the years following his undercover work with the CPUSA. Related to this file are the folders on “Yankee,” a woman from Massachusetts who from 1952 to 1972 sent Philbrick information and documents relating to organizations spanning the political spectrum, much of which he sent on to the FBI. Significant correspondents in the Subject File include James D. Bales, J. Edgar Hoover, William Loeb, Arthur G. McDowell, Reinhold Niebuhr, Ogden R. Reid, Henry Agard Wallace, and Robert Henry Winborne Welch.
The Speeches and Writings series features Philbrick's writing projects and lectures. The largest sections relate to his newspaper columns and speeches. Philbrick wrote a newspaper column titled “Red Underground” for the New York Herald Tribune from 1952 to 1958. A list of topics serves as an index to the columns. The Tribune files include responses from readers, attorneys, and individuals and organizations mentioned in the columns. The speeches section documents Philbrick's activities as a lecturer for over thirty years. Contracts, itineraries, and lecture requests indicate the types of groups that invited him to speak. The speaking engagements section contains correspondence, programs, and press coverage of his appearances. Titles of Philbrick's lectures include “Communism and Youth,” “The Christian Answer,” “Cybernetic Warfare,” “Red, White, and Pink,” and “Zero Hour for America.”
Another of Philbrick's writing projects was a series of newsletters sponsored by such organizations as Dollar Federal Savings and Loan of Columbus, Ohio, and the Schick Razor Company. Topics include Philbrick's concerns about the international communist conspiracy, the assassination of John F. Kennedy, and the Vietnam War. Articles by Philbrick were often reprinted in the various newsletters. Drafts and background material for the newsletters are filed under Dollar Hollar. Also in the Speeches and Writings series are articles, book reviews, letters to editors, childhood diaries, and unpublished and incomplete book projects on communism and religion and the assassination of President Kennedy.
The Miscellany series contains personal and family material as well as files relating to appearances by Philbrick on film, television, and radio. Press clippings in the biographical material section describe activities and events in Philbrick's life and provide clues as to which files throughout the collection have a direct connection to Philbrick. Included among the film, television, and radio material are files on Philbrick's own television projects, Red Report and World War III. Office files contain memoranda and draft correspondence that he prepared for staff while he was away on lecture tours. Card files include information on various people, many of whom Philbrick suspected of having communist connections. Legal files contain material related to a lawsuit between Philbrick and his attorney, Moses Frankel, who had worked as his agent in the 1950s and who negotiated his book and television deals. Family material includes items relating to his father, Guy Philbrick, a railroad trainman, and to Herbert Philbrick's second wife, Shirley.
The 2001 Addition consists of material received after the processing of the main portion of the Philbrick Papers was completed. It supplements each of the series and its arrangement reflects the organization of those series: general correspondence, Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA), I Led 3 Lives, subject file, speeches and writings, and miscellany. Items that complement the existing material include a scrapbook of press clippings relating to Philbrick's 1949 testimony in the Smith Act trials of communist leaders and files relating to his revised edition of I Led 3 Lives: Citizen, "Communist," Counterspy.
The 2023 Addition supplements the general correspondence series and the speeches and writings series from both the original portion and the 2001 Addition. This addition also includes scripts and research materials for thirty-five broadcasts of Philbrick's radio program, Let Freedom Ring. Additional material includes a small amount of biographical material, material related to church acitivities, and photographs of Philbrick.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is arranged in ten series:
General Correspondence, 1938-1993
Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA), 1940-1967
I Led 3 Lives, 1940-1972
Subject File, 1849-1997
Speeches and Writings, 1928-1992
Miscellany, 1886-1994
2001 Addition, 1925-1993
2023 Addition, 1947-1992
Oversize, 1949
Top Secret, 1946
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1938-1993 (Box 1-8)
  Letters received and sent.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1938-1954, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1955
    - Jan.-May, (2 folders)
    - June-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1956-1958, (9 folders)
  - 1959-1960, (8 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1961-1962, (9 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1963-1965, (9 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1966-1969, (11 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1970-1981, (12 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1982-1993, undated, (11 folders) (Box 8)
- Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA), 1940-1967 (Box 8-13)
  Reports, correspondence, handbills, transcripts, notes, newspaper clippings, and other printed matter relating to Philbrick's activities within the Communist Party, his work as an informant for the Federal Bureau of Investigation, and his testimony regarding American communism.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically therein.
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) See also Containers 94-96, same heading (Box 8)
    - 1941-1944, (5 folders)
    - 1945-1952, (11 folders) (Box 9)
  - Party activities
    - 1940, (2 folders)
    - 1941-1945, (9 folders) (Box 10)
    - 1946 -1947, (6 folders)
    - 1948, (2 folders) (Box 11, Box 12)
    - 1949, undated, (2 folders)
  - Testimony
    - 1949
      - Miscellany, (2 folders)
      - Transcripts, (5 folders); (3 folders) (Box 13)
    - 1951-1967, (10 folders)
- I Led 3 Lives, 1940-1972 (Box 13-28)
  Drafts, scripts, correspondence, memoranda, contracts, and notes relating to the book, television series, newspaper serialization, and other projects based on Philbrick's autobiography.
  Arranged alphabetically by format and chronologically therein.
  - Book (Box 13)
    - Contracts, 1951-1952, 1971
    - Correspondence
      - Complimentary copies, 1952, (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 14)
      - General, 1949-1972, undated, (5 folders)
    - Drafts
      - Outlines and summaries, 1949-1951, undated
      - Set 1, 1951, (5 folders)
      - Set 2, undated, (2 folders) (Box 15)
      - Set 3, 1951, (4 folders)
      - Set 4, undated, (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 16)
      - Fragments, 1951, undated
    - Financial statements, 1951-1956
    - Miscellany, 1951-1961, 1971-1972, undated, (2 folders)
    - Resource material, 1940-1951, undated, (3 folders)
    - Reviews, 1952
  - Proposed projects
    - Comic strip, 1954-1955
    - Motion picture, 1952-1956, 1963-1967, undated
  - Radio, 1952
  - Serialization (Box 17)
    - Alimyon (Philippines), 1958-1959, (2 folders)
    - New York Herald Tribune, 1951-1952, (2 folders)
    - Syndicated newspapers, 1952, undated, (2 folders)
  - Television
    - Correspondence, 1952-1965, (7 folders)
    - Financial statements, 1954-1964 (Box 18)
    - Miscellany, 1953-1958, 1969, undated, (2 folders)
    - Plot outlines and comments by Philbrick, 1953-1956, undated, (6 folders)
    - Scripts
      - No. 10, no title, Sept. 1953
      - No. 16, "Communist Cop," Nov. 1953
      - No. 36, no title, Mar. 1954
      - No. 40, "Counterfeit," June 1954
      - No. 41, "Relatives," June 1954
      - No. 42, "Close Factory," July 1954 (Box 19)
      - No. 43, "The Martyr," July 1954, undated
      - No. 44, no title, July 1954
      - No. 45, "Infiltration," July 1954
      - No. 46, "Assassination," July 1954
      - No. 47, "The Bomb," July-Aug. 1954, (2 folders)
      - No. 48, "Atomic Antidote," July-Aug. 1954, undated
      - No. 49, "Day Camp," Aug. 1954
      - No. 50, "The Guest," Aug. 1954
      - No. 51, "Charity," July-Aug. 1954
      - No. 52, "Narcotics," Aug. 1954 (Box 20)
      - No. 53, "Fifth Amendment," Aug. 1954, undated
      - No. 54, "Rest Home," Sept. 1954, undated
      - No. 55, "Deportation," Aug.-Sept. 1954
      - No. 56, "The Switch," Sept. 1954
      - No. 57, "Sweethearts for Servicemen," Sept. 1954, undated
      - No. 58, "Political Asylum," Sept. 1954, undated
      - No. 59, "A Very Moving Story," Aug. 1954
      - No. 60, "Mailing List," Sept.-Oct. 1954
      - No. 61, "Camera," Oct. 1954, undated
      - No. 62, "Minority Control," Oct. 1954, undated, (2 folders)
      - No. 63, "Comic Strip," Sept.-Oct. 1954
      - No. 64, "Goon Squad," Oct. 1954, undated (Box 21)
      - No. 65, "Commie Convicts," Sept.-Nov. 1954, (2 folders)
      - No. 66, "Investments," Oct.-Nov. 1954
      - No. 67, "The Son," Oct.-Dec. 1954, (2 folders)
      - No. 68, "Vandalism," Nov.-Dec. 1954, undated, (2 folders)
      - No. 69, "Brain Wash," Nov.-Dec. 1954
      - No. 70, "The Boss #2," Nov. 1954-Jan. 1955, undated, (2 folders)
      - No. 71, "Revolt," Nov. 1954-Jan. 1955 (Box 22)
      - No. 72, "Mr. & Mrs.," Dec. 1954-Jan. 1955, undated
      - No. 73, "Oil Field," Dec. 1954-Jan. 1955
      - No. 74, "Church Story," Jan.-Feb. 1955, undated
      - No. 75, "Lost Report," Jan.-Feb. 1955
      - No. 76, "Child Commie," Feb. 1955
      - No. 77, "Commie Dies," Feb. 1955, undated
      - No. 78, "Lost Identity," Jan.-Feb. 1955
      - No. 79, "Operation Rubout," July 1955
      - No. 80, no title, July 1955
      - No. 81, "Attack Area," July 1955, (2 folders)
      - No. 82, "Sacrifice," July 1955, undated (Box 23)
      - No. 84, "Athlete," Aug. 1955, undated
      - No. 85, "Lawyer," Aug. 1955, undated
      - No. 86, "Newsreel," July-Aug. 1955, undated, (2 folders)
      - No. 87, "Common Denominator," July-Sept. 1955
      - No. 88, "Stolen Passport," Sept. 1955, undated
      - No. 89, "Exchange Student," Aug.-Sept. 1955, undated, (2 folders)
      - No. 90, "Ex G.I.," Aug.-Oct. 1955 (Box 24)
      - No. 91, "Prisoner," July-Oct. 1955
      - No. 92, "Instruction Camp," Sept.-Oct. 1955
      - No. 93, "Second Courier," Oct. 1955
      - No. 94, "Phony Brother," Oct. 1955, undated
      - No. 95, "Trapped," Sept.-Oct. 1955
      - No. 96, "Mother-in-Law," Oct. 1955
      - No. 97, "Central American," Oct.-Nov. 1955, (2 folders)
      - No. 98, "Kidnap," Oct.-Nov. 1955
      - No. 99, "Historical Society," Oct.-Nov. 1955, (2 folders) (Box 25)
      - No. 100, "Hit and Run," Oct.-Nov. 1955, (2 folders)
      - No. 101, "New Member," Oct.-Dec. 1955
      - No. 102, "The Dead Man," Nov.-Dec. 1955, (2 folders)
      - No. 103, "Missing Man," Nov.-Dec. 1955, (2 folders)
      - No. 104, "Commie Photo," Dec. 1955 (Box 26)
      - No. 105, "Airman," Dec. 1955-Jan. 1956
      - No. 106, "Radioactive," Nov.-Dec. 1955
      - No. 107, "Inspectoscope," Dec. 1955-Jan. 1956, (2 folders)
      - No. 108, "Fiancé," Dec. 1955-Feb. 1956, (2 folders)
      - No. 109, "Public Idol," Dec. 1955-Feb. 1956
      - No. 110, "Counterspy's Wife," Dec. 1955-Mar. 1956, (2 folders)
      - No. 111, "Dynamite," Jan.-Feb. 1956, undated (Box 27)
      - No. 112, "Legation," Jan.-Feb. 1956
      - No. 113, "Discredit Police," Jan.-Feb. 1956, (2 folders)